你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到自动化漏洞发掘模块
welcome back to automated vulnerability discovery
今天我们要讨论的是符号执行
today we're talking about symbolic execution
动态符号执行
dynamic symbolic execution
当然这是一个动态分析
of course it's a dynamic analysis
这意味着为了分析代码
which means that in order to analyze what is going on with code
必须执行它
it has to execute it
我们开始吧
so let's roll on
动态符号执行的核心思想
the core idea of dynamic symbolic execution
是在所谓的符号数据域上模拟程序执行
is that you emulate the program on what is called a          symbolic data domain
CPU工作在1和0上
a typical cpu operates on 1s and 0s right
如果用read系统调用读入用户输入
if you read in user input using the read system call
你得到的是1和0
what you get are 1s and 0s
作为与程序交互的人
as a human interacting with the program
你不能给它发送一个未知值的变量
you can't send it some variable with an unknown value
但你可以创建一个模拟器来支持这个
but you could create an emulator that could support this
所以它可以是1 0或者x
so it could be a one a zero or x
然后随着你逐渐了解了
and then later on as you build up an understanding of
已知数据是什么
what data is known
未知数据是什么
what data is unknown
根据cmp比较未知数据
and as unknown data starts being checked using compare instructions
并基于比较结果跳转
those checks start being acted on using conditional jumps
你可以建立起一个公式
you can actually build up formula that
描述程序的行为
describe the behavior of the program
获得程序输入、检查条件和程序输出之间的关系
given the relationship between program input conditional  checks and program output
你模拟这个程序
so you emulate the program
提取出描述该程序的公式
you extract formulas that describe this program
然后加上想要的约束
and then you add desired constraints
所以如果你想要获得flag
so if you want to get the flag
我们会
we will say hey
我们希望程序不要输出incorrect
we want the program output to not be incorrect
我们把这个约束条件加到公式中
and we add this constraint to our formula
然后我们用约束求解器
and we use what is called a constraint solver
求解这个公式，得到未知数据的有效答案
to solve these formulas for valid answers for unknown      data
这就是符号执行
that is symbolic execution
其实没这么简单
it's actually not this simple
这是一个非常简化的观点
this is a very simplified view
我们将深入探讨为什么这并不简单
and we'll dive into why it's not simple
但首先让我们谈谈历史
but first let's talk about some history
我在defcon一个程序分析的演讲中
i tracked symbolic execution back for a talk i gave at       defcon about program analysis
追溯了符号执行的历史，到1975年
fairly far to 1975
1975年罗伯特·博耶
in 1975 Robert Boyer
现在是一所大学的名誉教授
now a professor Emeritus at one of the ut's
好像是德州大学奥斯汀分校
i want to say ut Austin
创建了一个叫做SELECT的系统
created a system called SELECT
一种通过符号执行来查找程序中的错误的系统
a system that did symbolic execution to find bugs in        programs
1975年，很久以前了，安全还没成一个单独的领域
1975 very long time ago before really security was a field
我觉得这太酷了
and i thought wow that's pretty cool
这比第一篇模糊测试论文发表的时间还要早
that's earlier than let's say the first fuzzing paper came    out
可能这就是源头了
this is probably it
但后来
but then
几周前
a couple weeks ago
在为竞争条件模块查找历史材料时，偶然发现
by chance while looking up the history of race conditions  for the race condition module
克劳德·香农的硕士还是学士论文来着
i stumbled on to the master's thesis or maybe Bachelor's thesis of Claude Shannon
如果你不认识
if you don't know
或者你通过香农的熵理论认识了他
or you might know Shannon from shannon's entropy
它是信息论的基本组成部分
a fundamental building block of information theory
如果你不知道的话
if you don't know it
我强烈建议你学习它
i highly recommend you learn it
它非常酷
it's very very cool
克劳德·香农在1938年
so Claude Shannon in 1938
在他的硕士论文中
for his master's thesis
写了一篇用符号分析继电器和交换电路的论文
wrote a paper about symbolic analysis of Relay and          switching circuits
他实际上
where he actually
将识别竞争条件，作为这种符号分析的一个应用
identified race conditions as an application of this sort of symbolic analysis
这不完全是我们所说的符号执行
it's not quite the symbolic execution we're talking about
但是很接近了
but it's close
而且这是在很久很久以前
and it is so long ago
于是我想这应该差不多了
so i thought okay finally almost
这都差不多是一百年前了
i mean almost a hundred years
差不多80年前
let's say you know almost 80 years ago
源头一定是这个了
this has got to be it
这应该是源头了
this is the the origin
超过了80年
or actually over 80 years ago
很酷
wow cool
事实证明我大错特错了
well it turns out i was off by a lot
你可能会问怎么会
and you might say how
怎么可能早于1938年呢
how can it be much earlier than 1938
实际上我们可以追溯到1842年
well we can dive back to 1842
追述到Ada lovelace
to Ada lovelace
和她对查尔斯·巴贝奇的分析机的分析
and her analyses of Charles Babbage's analytical engine
它被认为是首个现代计算机
what is a design that is the first thing recognizable as a   modernish computer
1842年Ada lovelace
in 1842 Ada lovelace
对查尔斯·巴贝奇设计的这台机器写了许多分析
wrote a number of analyses of this machine designed by Charles babbage
其中包括一个计算伯努利数的程序
and one of these included a program that computed
Bernulli numbers
历史上最早编写的程序之一
one of the first programs ever written in history
它是Ada lovelace写的
written by Ada lovelace
如果你看
and if you look she
这是她对这个程序的分析
this is a table of her analysis of this program
她一步一步地记录了每个操作的作用
she goes through step by step of what each operation does
以及结果是什么
and what the results are
各种寄存器中的值是什么
what the values are in the various registers
这些都是符号化的
and these are symbolic
她在1842年手工进行了符号执行
she is doing manual symbolic execution in 1842
这可能是最古老的分析示意图了
so this is probably the oldest analysis paradigm
我们将讨论从19世纪中期到现在的动态符号执行
we'll talk about dynamic symbolic execution from the mid 19th century to today
我们看看它是什么样的
let's see what it's like
如今的动态符号执行
today dynamic symbolic execution
会模拟代码，转化成数据公式
emulates code to convert it into math
这并不容易
this isn't easy right
我们在第一张幻灯片中看到的是一种直接的转换
what we saw in that first slide was kind of a straight shot conversion
实际上要复杂得多
what actually happens is a lot more complex
符号执行必须像普通CPU一样按顺序执行代码
symbolic execution has to execute code in sequence like a normal cpu
不同的是，它有一个可修改的模拟状态
the difference is it has an emulated state that it can mess with
我关掉相机
i'm going to disable my camera
这样你可以清楚地看到下一部分
so you can see this next part clearly
在符号模拟器中执行程序时
as you execute the program in a symbolic emulator
每当程序遇到分支时
every time the program encounters a branch
模拟器就会多分出一个内部状态
the symbolic emulator has to branch its internal state into two
一个状态根据一个条件，进入一个分支
one of these states gets one condition that would follow   the branch
另一个在该条件下，不会进入同一个分支
the other one gets the condition that would not follow the branch
这里的状态是，用户输入是42
here it is the user input being 42
与用户输入不是42
versus the user input not being 42
因为这是cmp指令检查
because that is what the compare instruction checked
jmp指令据此跳转的
and the jump instruction acted on
当这些状态分离后
then once those states diverge
他们的行为就不一样了
they start doing kind of different things
在状态A
so in state A
还有sendfile剩下的一部分
you have the leftovers of the sendfile call
实际上rax现在可能是flag的长度
actually probably rax would now be the length of the flag  or whatever
在状态B
in state B
你拿到了write的返回结果
you have the result of the write system call
rax可能是写入的字节数
rax is also probably going to be the amount of bytes        written
然后
and then of course
指定的约束
the constraint that specifies
这个状态中，是用户输入不能是42
the user input cannot be 42 here
这个状态中，是用户输入要是42
and has to be 42 here
并且对应的，这里的程序输出是INCORRECT
and the relationship of the program output being incorrect here
这里的输出是flag
and being whatever the flag value is there
这就是符号执行引擎的工作原理
that is how a symbolic execution engine works
现在我们看一个符号执行引擎的实际例子
and we're going to look at it in practice right now on a     symbolic execution engine
这是我和我优秀的同事在研究生时期创建的
that i created with my awesome colleagues back in my     graduate career
时至今日，在ASU的我们，依旧在此之上进行优化与研究
and that we still continue to improve develop and research on top of up to this day at ASU
这个系统就是angr
which and this system is angr
有很多符号执行引擎
there's a bunch of symbolic execution engines
有更多的，积极研发中的，符号执行引擎
there are more symbolic execution engines on their active development
相比于积极研发中的web浏览器
than there are web browsers on their active development
我不知道为什么会这样
i'm not sure why this is
但事情就是这样
but that is how it is
angr不是唯一的
angr is not the only game in town
但它是我最熟悉的
it is just what i'm most familiar with
并且是安装在pwn学院环境中的
and also what is installed in your containers
我们来看看
so let's take a look
我们有一个compare程序
we have our compare program
它接收一字节
that takes one byte
与另一个值比较，当然它是42
compares against a value of course it's 42
和幻灯片上的一模一样
it's exactly what was on the slide
不相等的话，会告诉我们 failure，而不是incorrect
and then tells us failure instead of incorrect
相等的话，输出success
or success if it's correct
我就没专门搞一个flag了
i didn't bother with a flag here
我们来看看如何用angr来解决这个问题
so let's check out how we would use angr to solve this
在ipython中导入它
import it in ipython
angr有一个项目的概念
angr has a concept of a project
基本就是，打开的二进制程序，以及它用的所有库
this is basically an open binary along with its libraries and everything
我们可以得到各种各样的信息
we can get various information
比如入口地址
such as the entry point
我们可以获取入口地址处的反汇编块
we can get the block disassemble the block at that entry  point
还有很多其他的东西
and various other things
我们能做的一件事，是所谓的模拟管理器
one thing that we can do is create what is called a           simulation manager
这就是我们说的模拟器
this is that emulator that we're talking about
或者说是angr模拟器的接口
or the interface to the angr emulator
它从一个激活状态开始
it starts out with an active state
这个状态有寄存器之类的东西
this is a state that has stuff like registers
这些是寄存器的初始值
these are the registers that start out with the values
程序刚开始执行时的值
that they start out with when the program begins             executing
还有内存
we have memory
例如，我们加载elf的基址
so for example if we load memory at the base of the elf
加载4字节
you can load four bytes
这会读入 7F E L F，和预料的一样
those read 7f e l f as expected
这很酷
so that's all very cool
实际上，让我
actually let's let me
哦，我没装
oh i don't have it installed
我得想想怎么解码
now i have to remember how to decode this
这是7f E L F
here is 7f elf
我们开始逐步执行
let's start stepping through execution
我们正在模拟这个程序
we are emulating the program
我们可以看到之前的状态
we can actually see the history of this state
怎么回事
oops what's going on
它在执行过程中走过的路径
the path that it took through the program executing
这意味着有一个条件跳转
this means that there was a conditional jump
但数学上只有一个条件可以满足
but only one condition could be satisfied mathematically
所以不会进入这个分支
so that cannot be taken
但是如果我们继续步入
but if we keep stepping
最终
eventually
状态会分裂
the state will split
实际上，我们可以执行run(until=)
in fact we can say run until
写一个python lambda函数
write a python lambda function
如果你不知道这是什么
if you don't know what this is
切到浏览器
swap out tab out
快速查一下
look it up real quick
回来
come back
lambda函数接收一个
lambda function takes a
该模拟管理器，作为参数
the same simulation manager as an argument
然后
and it says
计算停止执行的条件
and it just calculates a condition to stop executing at
这里是，执行到有一个以上的状态时
so this will say execute until there is more than one active state
现在有2个状态了
boom there's two active states now
发生了什么
so what happened
我们来看一看
let's take a look
这是两者的执行路径
here is the history of both
他们最后都执行的是
and the last thing they both executed of course
当然，因为直到最近，它们的路径都是相同的
because they were the same path until the same state until very recently
有2个能满足的条件的块
was this block with two satisfiable successors
这就是为什么模拟器中现在会有两个状态
that's why we now have two states in the emulator
我们来看看这是什么
let's take a look at what this is
是我们要找的cmp和jmp
and it's our compare and jump
很酷
cool
我还想给你们看一样东西
one more thing i want to show you
在一个状态中
on one state
我们有一个约束，是输入为42
we have a constraint that the input equals 42
另一个状态中
on the other one
约束为，输入不等于42
we have a constraint that the input does not equal 42
很酷吧
pretty cool huh
我们继续
let's push forward
这是
so this is
这些是活跃状态
these are the active states
我们要做的是
what we're gonna do
叫
what is called
我们执行到最后
we're gonna run until the end
直到
until program
直到所有状态都结束
until all states terminate
通常这是不会成功的
usually this is not successful
通常会像我们马上要讲到的
usually as we'll discuss in a second
这些分析通常规模非常大
these analyses actually are very very very not scalable
它们不会终止
they don't terminate
但是，不好意思
but excuse me
这是一个非常非常简单的程序，所以会成功退出
this was a very very simple program and they did
你可以看一下它们现在的约束条件
and again you can look at the constraints now
我们现在没有任何终结的状态了（口误）
we don't have any dead ended ones anymore
哦，抱歉，激活的状态，它们都是终结的状态
oh sorry active ones they're both dead ended
我们有这两种状态
so here we have these two states
一个的约束条件是等于42
one that has the constraint as equal
一个是不等于42
one as not equal
我们可以看的另一件事，是它们的标准输出
and another thing that we can look is their standard output
你可以称之为具体化
you can call concretize
具体化是
concretize is
具体化是查询约束求解器的过程
concretization is the process of querying a constraint solver
来解这个公式
to solve the formula
从
to go from
当然这些公式很简单
and of course these formulas are very simple
从数学公式，变成1与0
to go from mathematical formula to 1s and 0s
所以，在输入不是42的状态中
so on one state the state that is not 42
它输出failure
it says failure
在输入是42的状态中
the state that where the standard input was 42
在状态1中，输出是success
this state 1 it says success
很酷
very cool
我们也可以具体化
we can also concretize
使用相同的技术
using the same technique
用约束求解器，计算标准输入
with the constraint solvers standard input
所以成功状态
so on the state where we have a successful state
输入是一个星号
the input is a star
让我们来看一看
let's take a look
当然
and of course
输出的是success
that's a success
很酷
that is awesome
符号执行是最酷的工具
symbolic execution is the coolest kit on the block
我们不需要其他任何东西
we don't need anything else
我们就用它来探索软件
we'll just use this to explore software
识别漏洞
identify vulnerabilities
不幸的是，事实并非如此
unfortunately that is not the case
符号执行有严重的限制
symbolic execution has serious limitations
这些限制就是
and these limitations are that
它必须追踪每一条路径来理解正在发生的事情
it has to follow every path to understand what is going on
这是一个动态分析
it's a dynamic analysis
我们现在研究的程序非常简单
the program that we are looking at is very simple
只是比较是否是42
compares against 42
是的话，跳转获取flag
jumps to get the flag
如果你有稍微复杂一点的东西呢
what if you had something that is just just a tiny bit more complex
如果是调用atoi，ascii转整数
what if it called atoi ASCII to integer
然后再和42比较
and then compared against 42
你实际上发送的是字符42
so you actually send 4 2
我突然意识到，这不对
oh i realized obviously that's not solvable
我来快速修正一下
let me fix that real quick
好了，好多了
all right much better
我们读入两个字节
so we have we read in two bytes
然后调用atoi
and then we call atoi
如果你输入42
so if you type 42
那就会拿到这个correct
then you should get this correct
取决于atoi的实现方式
well it turns out that depending on the implementation of   atoi
符号执行无法解决这个问题了
symbolic execution can no longer solve this
想一下这样的atoi实现
consider this insane implementation of atoi
这不是一个很好的实现
it's not a very good implementation
但是程序分析的有趣之处在于
but the interesting thing about doing program analysis
你无法决定你要分析什么样的实现
is you don't get to decide what implementations you're
analyzing
你会分析你想要了解的程序代码
you analyze the code of the programs you want to get
some understanding of
这些程序可能用这种疯狂的方式编写atoi
and those programs might have atoi implementations
written in this insane way
这样我们该怎么办
so how would we approach this
我们在程序或函数执行时，跟踪执行者
let's just trace through the executor as it executes this
program or this function
我们从一个未知字符串开始
we start out with a string we don't know what is in it
它是一个无约束的，我们从标准输入读入的数据
it is unconstrained input data that we just read in from
standard in
当然，我们知道长度为2
of course we know this is size 2
我这里展示一下任意大小的情况
i'm just gonna show you for arbitrary sizes
在循环中的第一次，分裂出10个状态
the first time around the loop is we will split the state into ten
取决于哪些约束条件给到这个状态
depending on which of these constraints gets added to the state
我们会分成10个状态
we will split them all into ten
实际上是11个，还有一个是默认状态(break)
and actually 11 one for the default constraint
该状态输入的不是数字
where it's not a digit
我们要退出
i need to terminate it
我们会给每个状态添加不同的约束
and we will just add different constraints to each one
循环体执行一次后
so the first time through
我们就有了10个不同状态
we have ten different states
第二次执行
the second time
每一个状态都会再分出10个不同的状态
each of these states will split into ten different states
以此类推
and so on and so on
这就是符号执行中所谓的状态爆炸
this is what's called a state explosion in symbolic execution
这就是符号执行不可行的首要原因
and this is the number one reason that symbolic execution is non viable
我们看看在angr中是什么样
let's take a look at what happens in angr
我们来到ipython会话
let's grab our ipython session
我应该展示一下，我创造了一个相同的atoi.c
oh i should show you i created this exact thing atoi.c
它会输出success或failure
now it does success failure
我会展示一下，输入42会成功
i'll show you that it does work with 42
其它的不会
and not with other things
导入angr
import angr
加载atoi程序
load the atoi binary
创建模拟管理器
create the simulation manager
运行到有不止一个执行路径
let's run until there's more than one path
好，现在有两个执行路径了
okay there are two paths
现在看看再步入会怎样
now let's see what happens when we step
我们可以实时看到路径（状态）爆炸
let's we can see the path explosion happening in real time
就是这个
there it is
这些都在atoi函数中
this is all inside the atoi function
这是个坏消息
that's a a bad news
我们可以一直step很多次
and we can step for a very long time
有一个状态结束了
so there's one state that's dead ended
我们看看对应的输入是什么
let's see what its input is
当然，我们可以查询约束解答器
we can still of course query the constraint solver
在这个程序中，它实际上读取了10字节，而不是2字节
in this program i forgot it actually reads 10 bytes not two
很抱歉
sorry about that
它读入的都是空字节
so it read all null bytes
在这种情况下，第一个字节不是整数，于是atoi返回0
so this is the case where the first byte is not an integer
and atoi return zero
我们继续step，直到我们遇到第二个结束状态
let's keep stepping until we get a second dead ended guy
现在你可以看到
now you can see
花的时间越来越长了
it's taking longer and longer
因为它必须模拟187个块
because it has to emulate 187 blocks
每次我尝试step
every time i try to take a step forward
哦，来到了第二个结束状态
oh we have a second dead ended state
这是第一个数字为0的情况
this is the case where the first number is a zero
显然我们等不到运行完
obviously we're not going to sit through this
我再试一次
i'll do this one more time
哦
oops
下标超了一个
off by one
这是第一个数字为1的情况
is the case where it's a one
要经过很长时间和很多路径才能到达42
it'll take a very long time and a lot of paths to get to 42
there
我电脑内存耗尽都等不到它运行完
we won't reach it before my computer runs out of memory
路径爆炸是个问题
path explosion is a problem
有一些技术试图解决这个问题
there are some research techniques to try to solve it
这个特定情况很容易解决
this specific case can be easily solved
你可以使用一种技术合并状态
you can merge states using a technique
该技术使用复杂数学公式，将多种状态合并成一种
called vary testing into mathematically complex formula
but a single state
问题是，当你试图这么做的时候
the problem is when you try to do that
当你得到越来越复杂的公式
as you get more and more complex formula
你会开始让解答器不知所措
you start overwhelming the solvers themselves
约束是用所谓的SMT解答器来解答的
constraints are solved using what is called smt solvers
这种技术称为 可满足性模块化理论
this is a technique called satisfiability modular theories
这实际上是一个数学研究领域，研究如何解出这些约束
it's a mathematical area of research actually on how to
solve these constraints
SMT的基本思想是
and the basic idea of smt is
你有这些
you have these theories
这些理论本质上编码了不同类型的简化结果
the theories encode different types of simplifications
essentially
比如a*b=b*a
stuff like a times b equals b times a
更具体地说
or more specifically
a*b != b*a + 0以外的数
a times b is not equal to b times a plus anything but a zero
诸如此类的事情
and this sort of thing
所以我们尝试了一些数学化简
so we try a bunch of math simplifications
我们会检查一些常见情况
we check against common cases
看是否能用这些化简，轻易解决问题
we check if something could be trivially solved using these simplifications
如果不能
if not
我们继续尝试不同的理论
we keep trying different theories
直到我们耗尽了所有的理论
eventually we run out of theories
用逻辑表达式构建一个模型
we synthesize a circuit
它表示实际涉及的比特
that represents the actual bits involved
即使这些bit是未知的
even if those bits are unknown
然后通过布尔可满足性解决问题
and then we resort to boolean satisfiability
因为现在这些位是布尔值了
because now these bits are booleans
1和0
ones and zeros
布尔可满足性称为SAT
Boolean SATisfiability is called SAT
这是一个NP完全问题
it is a NP Complete problem
实际上是第一个被证明是NP完全的问题
actually the first problem to be proven to be NP Complete
这意味着我们没有一个多项式时间的算法来解决这个问题
that means that we do not have a polynomial time
algorithm that can solve this
求解SAT的算法是指数型的
algorithms that solve SAT are exponential
或者只是次指数
or just sub exponential
所以解决复杂的程序会很慢
so it can be very slow to solve complex programs
你饿死在电脑前，它可能都不会结束
as in it might not terminate before you starve to death in
front of your computer
结论就是，当面对复杂数据，复杂操作时
the takeaway here is faced with complex data complex
operations
符号执行会失败
symbolic executions fail
不只是路径爆炸问题
not just due to path explosion
也由于约束求解的局限性
but also due to constraint solving limitations
最后还有一个环境建模的问题
and finally there's a problem of modeling the environment
你看到我们在angr中模拟一切
you saw that we were emulating everything in angr
模拟CPU实际上很容易
emulating the cpu is actually easy
我改一下错别字
let me fix that typo there
模拟CPU相对容易
emulating the cpu is relatively easy
有现成的支持
there's existing support
我不想深入挖掘它
i don't want drill down that deeply
基本就是，我们使用现有的代码
but basically we use existing code
来翻译x86 arm MIPS或其它架构
to translate x86 arm mips whatever architecture we're
working on
到同一种之后我们模拟的语言
to a common language that we then emulate
这并不难
that's not hard
困难的是模仿操作系统
what's hard is emulating the os
read很简单，对吧
read is simple right
当read系统调用被调用，会从标准输入读取数据
a read system called that gets data from standard in
但load_module呢
but what about load_module
它是一个加载内核模块的系统调用
a system call that loads a kernel module
显然，我们不会运行整个内核
obviously we don't run the whole kernel
如果你想运行整个内核
and if you try to run the whole kernel
那么我们会遇到路径爆炸问题
then we'd run into the scalability issues of path explosion
等等......
and so on
所以这三个限制严重阻碍了符号执行的发展
so these three limitations really really heavily hold
symbolic executions back
如迈克尔·扎莱夫斯基的那句话
and be reminded of the quote by Michael Zalewski
他是世界上最成功fuzzer的创造者
the creator of the most successful fuzzer in the world
符号执行
that the uses of symbolic execution
动态符号执行
concolic execution
静态分析
static analysis
以及其他新兴的
and other emerging technologies
寻找复杂的、非结构化和无注释代码中的漏洞的技术
to spot substantial vulnerabilities in complex unstructured and non annotated code
还处在婴儿期
are still in their infancy
请注意，他说的不是模糊测试技术
note he's not talking about fuzzers
他在说这些东西
he's talking about this stuff
这是一个活跃的研究领域
this is an active area of research
世界上有很多学者
a lot of academics around the world
包括我在亚利桑那州立大学实验室的人
including people in my lab at asu
和我的同事
along with my colleagues
我们正在研究这个
we're working on this
如果你感兴趣，请告诉我们
if you're interested let us know